[MUSIC]
>> Stanford University. >> Okay, well, this is
lecture six of Stanford SC193 P Spring of 2016. And today we
are gonna dive in more into this topic of multiple MVCs.
If you remember, last lecture I talked a little about
multiple MVCs and how we can combine them with tab bars,
split view controllers and navigation controllers. And
we showed a little bit how to wire them up. Well, today, I'm
gonna talk a little about how we transition between them,
right? It's one thing to wire them up in our storyboard, but
as the user navigates our user interface, clicks on buttons
and stuff, we want to navigate between these MVCs, okay?
And then, time permitting at the end, I'm gonna talk
a little bit more about this view controller lifecycle, the
thing that I always delete. Okay? Those two methods.
There's a few more methods in the view controller lifecycle
that I'm gonna talk about, and again, time permitting,
I'll do a quick little demo at the end. All right.
So, segues. Okay, we've wired up these controllers of
controllers like tab bar split fuse navigation controllers,
and we've got all of our nice MVCs, and
now we want to transition between them.
We call those transitions segues, right?
The word segue in English means a transition. And
there's really four major kinds of segues.
I'm gonna talk about some more rare segues towards the end of
the quarter, but the main segues that you're gonna wire
up in a story board, one is called a show segue.
So, remember the navigation controller that's the stack of
cards, right? The settings app I showed you where you're
putting more stacks on the card. Well, transitioning to
put a new card on the stack, okay, is done using a show,
what we call a show sequeway cuz it shows another MVP or
MVC. I'm thinking about Steph Curry, I guess, okay?
MVC. And then, show detail is if you have a split view,
okay, and something happens in the master and
you want to show an MVC, a different MVC in the detail,
okay? Show detail, that's the detail of a split view.
Show detail also works in a navigation controller,
okay? So, if you do show detail, it's this really
the same as show in a navigation controller, unless
that navigation controller is inside of a split view, okay?
Show and show detail would be the same. But
if a navigation controller's inside a split view,
then show means show it in the Navigation Controller, and
Show Detail means show it in the Split View Controller,
right? Show the detail. Then there's Modal and Popover,
I'm not gonna talk about those today. Modal is basically
segue into takeover the entire screen with another MVC, okay?
And a popover is almost exactly the same except for
instead of taking over the entire screen,
it still takes over the entire screen in terms of input, but
it draws it in a little popover window and
everything else is kind of grayed out and
you can click on the grayed out to dismiss the popover.
Okay? So those are the major kinds of segue that you wire
up in your story boards.
So, we're gonna talk about navigation controllers,
split view controllers, tab bar today.
So, for navigation and split view controllers,
we're talking about show and show detail, okay?
So, we're gonna talk about today. All right. It's very
important to understand that segue virtually
always create a new MVC. Okay? If you segue to an MVC,
it's going to create it. You rarely, extremely rare,
there's only one kind of segue where you're gonna segue to
an MVC that already exists. Okay? So, segues create new
MVCs, okay? Super important to understand. That's even true
in a split view. If you do a show detailed segue,
it replaces the MVC that's in the detail side.
That's why we sometimes call a show detail a replace segue,
okay? That's kind of its old name. All right? So, how do we
make these segues happen, okay? Just like we always do,
we control drag, okay? Just like we
control drag to wire up our MVCs to our split view
control, navigation control, we're also gonna control drag
to determine how they segue up to each other, okay? How they
transition. It's also possible to make segues happen in code.
There's a method you call that says do this segue,
perform segue, it's called, okay? So
here is something wired up as of our last lecture, here.
I've got a split view controller,
and the detail is this little graphing thing at the bottom.
And the master is a navigation controller with
your little calculator view controller right there, okay?
That calculator view controller up there,
looking at this side today, that calculator up there might
be exactly the same MVC as the one you're building in your
homework, okay? All right? So, if we want to add a button to
the calculator that caused this graph to show,
maybe graph what's in your calculator. Wouldn't that be
cool? Then we would Ctrl-drag from that little button.
Can hardly see that button, but it's there. Ctrl-drag to
the MVC we wanna segue to. Okay? So, that's how it works.
You would just Ctrl-drag to. Now, when you Ctrl-drag to,
it's gonna put up a little black window here,
which I'll zoom in on, which is going to ask you what kind
of segue do you want. Do you want a show? A show detail?
A modal? Or a popover? Okay? So if you want this to appear
as the detail in a split view, you're gonna pick Show Detail.
Otherwise, it's just in a navigation controller,
you're gonna pick Show, okay? Again, we'll talk about
the other two later in the quarter. All right?
So, you've got that wired up. As soon as you do that,
you've get this little guy appearing here,
this line with a little thing in the middle here.
This is the segue. Okay? And this segue,
just like a button or anything else, is inspectable. So
if you go over here to the inspector and inspect it,
it's going to let you set some things about the segue.
The most important thing is its identifier, okay?
Every segue needs an identifier, because in your
code, you're gonna have to refer to that segue,
and you do it by name. By this identifier.
That's how you're gonna refer to this in your code.
So it's critical that you give your segues names, okay?
This identifier thing. And
we'll see that in the demo. And the name of
the identifier should probably describe what the segue does.
It's usually a verb, like a verb phrase like show graph,
do something. Cuz that's what segues do, they do something.
So it's usually some kind of verb phrase. Okay. So, what,
so, where in our code are we gonna use that identifier for
the segue?
It's really two places. One place that we don't use too
much is when we want to make that segue happen from code.
And we can do that with this method in UI view controller,
okay? You have your controller.
You all know what that is, okay? It's called perform
segue with identifier. You give it the identifier, and
then you can pass any object you want as the sender, okay?
The sender is the object that is causing the segue to
happen. Often that's a button, okay? But when you're doing it
from code, you can send any object really that you want.
Okay? And you'll see why we need that in a moment. Okay?
So that's one reason you need the identifier.
But a much more important reason is because when a segue
happens, the MVC your segueing to,
usually needs to be prepared to come on screen. Okay?
It needs some information.
Maybe it needs it's model to be set. That's a common thing.
Maybe it needs some of it's drawing attributes to be set,
okay? So that is happening in this preparation.
So, this is so important.
I'm gonna talk about the preparation in detail. Now,
the preparation happens with a method that is sent to
the view controller that is causing this segue to happen.
Not the view controller on
the other end that's being created, but
the one that is causing it to happen, okay?
That view controller is gonna be sent this message,
prepare for segue. Okay? And it's job in this method is
to prepare the MVC that's being created by the segue to
do what it wants to do. Now, it's really important to
understand with this multi-MVC world, that it's object
oriented in that each MVC kind of has it's own world.
Okay, they don't really wanna be talking back to each other.
And the MVC on the ender end of a segue is really part
of the view of the MVC that's causing the segue. Remember
those graphics that I told you? So we really can't talk
back to the one causing the segue. We would have to use
some kind of blind structured communication because the view
is not really allowed to talk to its controller, except for
in these structured ways, right?
The controller can talk to the view,
no problem. And he's going to here. This is going to be
the controller talking to its view by preparing
that MVC. But
you really wanna think of MVCs as living in their own world,
self-contained, they have some public API,
you set things in their public API, and they do what they do,
okay? It's very tempting when you're writing code,
especially maybe a lot of the code that you've written so
far in classes, to think, well, I can just put a method
here and a method there, and they can all call each other,
and it's all fine. But it's not, you need to start
thinking in terms of programming interfaces, okay,
encapsulation, true object oriented programming here.
Okay, I made you think about that a little bit in your
calculator brain and the calculator view controller,
assignment with
right? The calculator brain has a public API,
it's very clear what the public methods are,
those are the only methods a controller can use, okay?
Hopefully you didn't write your assignment,
where they're each calling, private messaging each other,
or things like that, okay? There's gotta be well-defined,
what those objects encapsulate, okay.
That's object oriented programming. So
same thing here, but at the whole MVC level, right?
We want the MVCs to be well-defined in what they do.
All right, so let's talk about prepareForSegue here and,
how you make it work, what all the parts of it are, okay? So
what it does,
first of all, you have the arguments here for
prepareForSegue. The first argument is the segue. So
this is a instance of a class called UIStoryboardSegue.
And it contains interesting information about the segue,
most notably the identifier.
Okay, that identifier we typed in the inspector, and also,
the controller of the MVC that you're segueing to.
It just created it, and you can, cuz remember,
segue is always created an MVC, so it just created
that thing, and you can get a pointer to it
from this segue argument right here, one of the properties on
UIStoryboardSegue is the destination view controller.
Okay, this other argument here, sender,
it's the same sender as was in perform segue with identifier.
This is just who caused this segue to happen. Usually,
it's a button, okay. But it could be any object if you,
if it started in code with perform segue with identifier,
okay? So we'll, we'll see this in the demo sometimes why you
would wanna know who this is, okay? All right, so
here's the identifier,
I'm getting it with the, var here called identifier,
right, the property off of the segue thing.
I'm checking here to make sure it's not nil. Because someone
might have created a segue in the storyboard, and
they forgot to set the identifier or
they didn't set the identifier. So
it could be nil, so
I'm checking to make sure it's not nil here. And then
I'm switching on it, okay? So I'm gonna switch on it.
And in this case, I'm gonna look for Show Graph,
which is in my previous slide, that's what I called,
that's what the identifier for that thing was.
And when I see that this is a Show Graph segue, then
I'm going to try and prepare the destination of the segue,
assuming that it is some sort of graph controller, right,
some code controller,
controller of an MVC that shows the graph. So
I'm gonna have to prepare it, I'm gonna have to prepare it,
okay. So the first thing that I'm gonna do is I'm gonna look
at the destination view controller of the segue, where
we're segueing to, okay. And I'm gonna see if it's a graph
controller. And it better be, because that's the only
way I know how to prepare for a segue called Show Graph. So
this thing better be, but I am doing if let with as to,
to see if it is, because destination view controller,
its type is just UIViewController, okay. So
I need to cast it with as just like I cast any
object sometimes with as.
Here I'm gonna cast this view controller, if I can,
to be a specific kind of controller that I'm expecting
this segue to be segueing to. Okay, so in this case,
some sort of graph controller of some sort. All right,
now once I've done that, now VC right here is gonna be
of type graph controller. Okay, that's what if let
this as that does, right, inside this curly brace,
vc is gonna be of type graph controller. And so I can start
sending messages and setting properties, public ones only,
of this controller in order to prepare it to do its job. So
if it's a graph controller, I don't know,
it might wanna know the axes, the range of the axes.
Somehow it might wanna know what function it's graphing,
I don't know. Okay, but that is happening in here,
where I'm preparing this graph controller that just got
created cuz of a segue to do what it does. Okay, questions
about that? All right, so it's really important
to understand, and that's why it's in red here, I don't put
things in red very often. But it's in red that when you're
doing this prepare of that destination view controller,
it was only just created just now, okay, femtoseconds ago,
okay. So its outlets have not been set, okay. This happens
before its outlets are set. This is quite annoying, okay,
because usually when you wanna prepare a view controller,
you wanna set things up in its outlets, like a calculator
one, you'd want to set something in the display or
something like that. But you can't do that, okay,
unfortunately, you can't do that.
This is happening before your outlets are set, so
you have to just give it the data it wants, and you're just
gonna have to hold on to that data. And then after its
outlets are set, it can start parceling that out to its UI,
okay? You will, at least once this quarter, get a crash,
because you'll start preparing some view controller.
You'll start accessing its outlets, it goes out with your
still nil, and you're gonna get optional nil was
accessed, okay. I'm gonna do it in my demo just to show
you it happening because it can happen so much.
All right, okay, so that's preparing,
super important part of segues, okay, so preparing.
Now there's a method you can also implement in your view
controller in addition to prepareForSegue called,
shouldPerformSegueWithIdentif- ier, okay.
And that is basically gonna return a bool, whether or
not that segue should happen. So you can prevent it, for
example, let's say in your calculator,
let's say you had a button that did a graph, and
let's say it was a partial result, so
you couldn't really graph it. This might return false, okay?
And maybe you'll see that on your homework. All right, so
the demo I'm gonna do is I'm gonna take FaceIt,
that we have so far that draws that face, I'm gonna add
a second MVC, okay. And this MVC's gonna have some emotions
listened in it, and when you click on them,
it's gonna show a face that reflects that emotion, okay?
So I'm gonna have two MVCs, and
we're gonna hook them up. Okay,
so here we are back in FaceIt, exactly where we were.
I haven't, added anything or changed anything, right?
So we've got our face view controller right here,
it's got its model, which is a facial expression. And
then it's got its view, which is this face view thing right
here. We add some gestures, we update our UI when this thing
is first set, our update UI just takes the model,
all these things out of the model, okay? And
it turns them into things in the view,
and and these are just the handlers for
these gestures. And that's it, so
that's all we have in our controller. And our story
board is really, really simple, it only has this one
view controller, okay, this face view controller. And
what I'm gonna do right off the bat is add another MVC.
So how do you add another MVC to your storyboard?
Well, you go over here to your object palette, and just like
from your object palette, you can do things like, adding
buttons and labels, you can also add entirely new MVCs.
And the way you do that is by grabbing this thing called
view controller at the top. In dragging it out into your
storyboard, okay. You can put it right there.
You can move things around wherever you want. Okay, so
now I have two MVCs in here. One really interesting thing
to note is that an NVC always need to have a custom class.
Okay, if it doesn't have a custom class,
where are you going to put your outlets and actions and
all that stuff. So just like this view controller,
if you look at it's identity inspector, remember we changed
it's identity and the identity inspector to be face
view controller, okay. So that makes it so
that this class is the controller for that thing, so
it has a model and outlets and things like that. Okay we need
to do the exact same thing with this view controller.
It needs to have a custom class. So the way you create
classes, you'll remember just like we did when we created
Face view for example. Is we do new file here. Okay so
I'm do new file. It's going to be iOS source, It's going to
be Coco Touch class because it's going to be a sub class
of UI view controller. Just like Face View controller was.
So I'm gonna double click here. Here, subclass of,
this is good, okay. Remember we did UI View before,
now we want UI View controller as our class. We don't want
to call it view controller, that's a very generic name, so
I'm gonna call it Emotions View Controller because that's
what it shows. This view controller shows emotions,
okay. Put it in the same place we always put it,
right here, same same as all our other code.
And here we go. Here's our emotions view controller,
again I'm going to remove these few controller
life cycle methods for now. But
notice also when I created this,
I got this little method. What is this method? Prepare for
segue. Okay, segues are so important to have in multiple
view controllers. That when it gives you a blank one, it
always gives you prepare for segue commented out, but it
knows you're almost certainly gonna want to prepare for
segue. Okay, that's how important this is. And indeed
we are gonna have to implement this if we want clicking on
emotions to go to our other MVC and do things, okay?
But we're not going to do this right now. The next
thing we're going to do, and you'll forget this step, okay?
You will for sure forget this step multiple times.
Which is we have to remember to go here and set in
the identity inspector, the class of this thing to be that
emotion's view controller. A lot of times you will create
that emotion view control, you just dive right in,
you start programming, and you forget to do this, and then
you cannot connect any of your outlets, and you are like,
what is wrong with this thing? Okay, well this is why.
You forgot to type your identity, here,
okay? So, now I have two, you see? This one says emotions
view controller and this says face view controller, so
two NVCs. Notice this little arrow right here.
You see this arrow? This arrow tells the app when it runs,
start with this view controller. So
if I were to run right now it would show the face, but
if I wanted to show my new view controller first I can
just pick this arrow up and drop it on this one.
Okay, so let's go ahead and run actually to verify that.
We should get a nice blank screen. Okay?
Here it is. Nice blank screen, working perfectly. Now,
one thing to notice, also is, it, I got a warning here.
Look, see this warning? Scene is unreachable due to lack of
entry points. It's talking about this scene,
okay? By the way, we call these MVCs in the storyboard.
This is called a scene. Okay? A scene. So this scene
is unreachable, because this arrow doesn't point to it.
And nothing in here segues to it. So you can't get to it,
okay, which makes sense. So
it's good that it's warning us about that. All right let me
build the UI of this guy right here. Okay? As I said it's
just gonna have some emotions in here that you can click on.
Normally you probably wanna do this with the table view.
Okay a table and extensible list of them.
But I can't I'm not teaching a table view until next week.
So we're gonna use buttons. All right?
So I'm just drag out four buttons here to be my
the four emotions that I am going to have here.
Sorry, put this in here.
And when I drag it out, it does not really matter where I
put it because I am going to stack view them. So
let us go ahead and make the font a little bigger here, 40
point. And so what buttons do we wanna have here? How about
an angry button and we'll have three other buttons.
How about happy and how about worried? Is that a,
an emotion, worried? I don't, I don't know.
It's good to make a face of it though. How about mischievous?
Mischievous, is that how you spell that?
Again I'm not sure that's an emotion, but
it makes a good face. Okay so here I have my things,
I'm going to stack view these.
Just going to select them all and go embed in stack view.
I don't want them left aligned like this, so
I'm going to change their alignment to fill the space.
I'll do fill equally although they're all the same font so
they're all gonna be the same height anyway so
it doesn't really matter there. So,
I want these words to always be in the middle of my screen,
even if I'm rotated like if I'm in landscape or
portrait, I always want them in the middle. So I'm gonna
use the dash blue lines to put it right in the middle.
And now you're going to do the same trick we did before,
which was rest to suggested constraints and
it's going to use those blue lines
to suggest some constraints to constrain this stack for
you on here. And let's go look what it suggested,
remember to do that we go over here to the size inspector.
We go down to where it says constraints, and sure enough,
align the center in the x-axis to superview and
align the center in the y-axis to superview. Perfect,
exactly what I want. So now if I run, it's gonna center this
horizontally and vertically. Okay, even if I'm in
landscape. Okay? So now, I've built this UI. Great,
it's exactly what I want. And I had now have two NVCs. Now,
I'm gonna show you all three ways of combining NVCs, tab
bars, split view controllers, and navigation controllers.
Let's start with tab bar controller, okay? How would I
put these two things one in its, each in its own tab?
Well, I'm gonna go down here, okay? To our object pallet.
And if you look, about six or seven down, there's this.
Tab bar controller, you see that? And if I drag this
out here, okay, it'll put this tab bar out here.
It unfortunately also brings some extra MVCs here,
these little blank MVCs that I don't want. So I'm just gonna
click on those and delete them. So get rid of that one.
And get rid of that one. So all I have now is my tab bar
controller. If you can read that, I'll zoom in a little.
Okay see tab bar controller and then I've got my two
MVC's here that I created. My emotions view controller and
my face view controller. Now I for sure want
the app to start with the tab bar controller, so I'm going
to move that arrow. This is another thing you'll forget.
You'll forget to move this arrow. Okay. And
now I just want this to be in one tab and this in the other.
I just do that with control drag. So control
drag to this one, I'm going to hook up this view controllers.
Remember the view controllers
property in a tab bar is just an array of all the tabs.
Okay, the MVCs is there in the tabs and do this one also,
that in the view controllers array, okay. You can even see
it's already starting to put the tabs on the bottom.
If you wanted to edit what's in these tabs, like the names,
you think, you double click down here something, but no,
because this is the Tab Bar Controller and these titles
and images are all set by the MVCs inside. Okay,
in an object oriented way, right. So, if you wanted to
set this you would actually go to each one of them.
And you can even double click right here and put in whatever
you want. You can also click here and inspect them, okay,
if you go to the inspector, you can set images and also
a bunch of system ones. Okay, so that's how you set that.
So this is what our Storyboard looks like right now and
if we run this. We'll see that we get a tab bar.
See, it's got two tabs at the bottom here. And
if I click between them, I get my two MVCs.
Now this is completely inappropriate to what I'm
building here because I would never want, if I clicked on
one of these, for it to switch over to this tab, okay?
That's because when you do a tab bar UI, listen closely,
the user owns which tab is showing, okay?
They get to choose by clicking on those tabs. You don't get
to choose by throwing them over to one, okay?
That is not appropriate for tab bar. Everyone got that? So
things in a tab bar UI tend to be independent things,
things that don't segue from one to another,
you can't even make a segue from one tab to another, so no
such segue. So we don't want to do a tab bar controller
here, so I'm just going to delete my tab bar controller,
okay? Now one thing you'll notice when I deleted my tab
bar controller is, where's my arrow? Okay, it's gone. So
now it's not going to, if I run, I'm actually going to get
an error in the console saying I don't know where to start
in my storyboard, basically. So how do you get that arrow
back? Just click the one you want
the arrow to be on, inspect it, and go right down here,
very top, is initial view controller,
if you turn that on, the arrow will come back there, okay?
And you can move it, okay, down to here if you want.
Okay? All right, so let's talk about split view controller.
We haven't even done anything with iPad at all in this class
目前为止，这门课还没有任何涉及 iPad 应用的内容
yet. So this is our first time doing it and we're gonna put
所以现在是我们第一次讨论关于
this in split view controller where this is the master and
有 master controller 和 detail controller 的
this is the detail, makes sense, right?
split view controller 明白了没？
Because we're clicking in the master,
我们点这个展示 master controller
this will be the detail that's shown from clicking on this.
点这个展示 detail controller
So how do we do a split view controller?
我们怎么处理一个 split view controller 呢？
Same way as tab bar. I'm gonna go down here, right below tab
给 tab bar 的一样，我在这里
bar is split view controller. I'm gonna drag that out,
Tab Bar Controller 下面就是这个 Split View Controller
I get a whole bunch of junk with it. We'll zoom out so
把这个拖出来，我就得到了一大堆垃圾(controller)
you can see it. Okay. See, I got all these extra things, so
缩小了你就看见了，我得到了好多额外的东西
I'm gonna, click on these extra things and
所以我要把这些额外的统统删掉
delete them, don't want any of them. Okay. So I just have
一个都不想留，所以我现在只有
the split view controller and my two guys here.
这个 split view controller 和 刚刚那两个 controller
Of course I want the split view controller, again,
我想让这个 split view controller 变为最早展示出来
to be the start so I'm going to put the arrow there. And
所以我把箭头放在这里
then, in order to hook up master and detail, Ctrl+Drag.
然后，为了将 master、detail 与 split view controller 联系起来
Master, Ctrl+Drag, detail. Okay,
Ctrl+Drag 选择 Master，Ctrl+Drag 选择 detail
so that's how we set it up, couldn't be simpler. So let's
我们就是这么建立起他们的关系，再简单不过了
run, but let's run on iPad, so I'm gonna, on iPad 2 here,
现在在 iPad 上运行，我用 iPad 2 模拟器
we'll run and hopefully this will show up as a master and
运行起来，希望这个会作为 master
this will be the detail. All right. So here's the iPad.
这个会作为 detail 展示出来，这是 iPad
Here's the detail. You notice that when it's in portrait
这是 detail controller，你可能注意到当在竖屏状态下
it fills the screen with the detail,
detail controller 充满了屏幕
and you get the master by dragging out from the side.
通过拖动侧边，master controller 就展示出来了
See that? Okay? That's how you get the master. And
看到了吗？竖屏就通过这种方式看到 master controller
if you're in landscape,
如果横过来，变成横屏状态
then they're both onscreen at the same time. Now, if I click
master 和 detail 就在屏幕上同时展示出来
on these, I want this face to show me angry, show me happy,
如果我点 Angry，我希望这个脸变成生气的样子
show me worried, show me mischievous, okay?
变成高兴、变成担忧、变成淘气的样子
So how do I do that? This is where the segues come in.
这怎么做呢？这时我们就需要用到 segue 了
Okay? This is where we have to have this view controller
我们需要让这个 view controller 转场
segue to create a new one of these and
然后 create 一个detail controller
when it creates this, it's going to create it with
当 create 时，会 create 一个有确切表情值的 controller
the proper facial expression, okay? So it's going to prepare
所以，它会准备好表情值
it with a facial expression and show it. Okay? So
然后将这个确切的表情展示出来
let's do those segues. The way we do segues, also Ctrl+Drag.
我们来设置这些转场，同样是 Ctrl Drag 设置
So, let me zoom in here so you can see this. All right?
我放大点你就可以看到了
I'm gonna Ctrl+Drag from whichever of these buttons
我按住 segue 开始的 button，然后 Ctrl + Drag
I want to segue from. I'm gonna segue from all four, so
我想从这4个button开始连 segue
I'm gonna have four segues. So like angry here I'm
所以我应该有4个segue，像从这里按住 angry button
just gonna Ctrl+Drag down to this MVC. And let go.
然后 Ctrl + Drag 到这个 MVC，然后松手
And it says, well what kind of segue do you want?
这里会让你选择你想要的 segue 类型
Show, show detail, modally or
Show, show detail, modally 或者是
pop over. Well, we're in the split view controller here so
pop over。因为我们用的是 split 控制器，所以
I want to show detail, right? Split view. Master detail.
我选择 show detail
Show detail. Bam. There it is right there. Okay?
这个是split view，然后 master detail 用 show detail 连接，对吧？
Created this little thing here. That's my segue. And
做了这些工作，这就是我的 segue
this segue can be inspected. You can see it up here, okay?
这些 segue 是可以被检查的，你可以在这里看到他们
This is the attributes inspector. And it's got
这是属性检查器，会显示 show detail 的类型
the kind of show detail, also known as a replace segue.
也常常被叫做 replace segue
It animates, it shows that this segue is going to happen
这是 Animates，这个说明这个 segue 可以用动画的形式展现
in an animated fashion, so it's going to slide in or
是滑进或者别的方式
whatever. It's not always makes sense to animate but
并不总是可以选择 Animates 的，有时候可以
sometimes it does. Class and module, don't worry about
有时候不行，不用担心这些，比如 Class 和 Module
that. That's for creating your own custom segues,
这些帮助你设置你自定义的 segue
which we're not going to talk about in this class.
这些内容有一些超前，所以我们这节课不会讨论到
A little bit too advanced. And then, here is the all
最重要的属性是 identifier
important identifier. So here, we have to give any string
我们需要用字符串来唯一确定这个segue
we want that identifies this segue. So I could call this,
比如，我可以叫这个segue
for example, the angry segue, maybe I'd want a verb
为 angry segue
phrase like show anger or something like that but
我应该用一个动词，比如 show anger 或者
it's fine also maybe to have a nice simple word like anger.
就是一个单一的明确的名词，像 anger
So that's my angry segue right there.
所以，这是我的 angry segue
Okay. And so now let's wire up the other ones, Ctrl+Drag this
好，现在我们连一下剩余的控件
one down here. This one is also going to be show detail.
在这里按 Ctrl + Drag，这个是 show detail
They're all going to be show detail. I'll do worried also.
我想这个也应该是 show detail
Show detail, oops, not present modally, get rid of that.
oops，不是 present modally，删掉这个
Alright. Then here. Show detail.
这个也是 Show detail
Mischievous. Show detail.
给淘气的也连上Show detail segue
Okay, now I need to set the identifier for all of these.
现在，我需要给这些 segue 都设置 identifier 作为唯一标示
What's really cool is if I click on one it'll tell me who
特别酷的是，如果我点击一个 segue，他会显示
the sender of this segue is. So there's worried, okay.
这个 segue 的发送者是哪一个，这个是 worried
Worried. Here is happy, and
这个是 happy
we'll call this my happy segue.
我想把这个叫 happy segue
This one, angry already set up. This one, mischievous,
这个，angry 已经设置好了
okay. Mischievous. Hopefully I spelled that right. Okay, so
这个是 Mischievous，希望我正确地拼写了这几个词
now we've got these segues set up so let's run and
现在我设置了这几个 segue，然后运行一下
see what happens here. All right, angry, happy,
看看会发生什么
still nothing's happening. What is the problem here?
什么也没发生，问题出在什么地方呢？
Okay, well, it is actually segueing here.
Okay，这确实是 segue 的问题
It's replacing that face with a new MVC, but
程序用了新的 MVC 来替换这张脸
that new face has not been prepared to show the emotion
但是，这个新 face 还没有准备好展示这个表情
we want so it's just showing the default emotion,
所以它仅仅展示在 storyboard 中展现的
whatever happened to be in our storyboard, right?
默认表情，对吗？
This face right here just happens to be, or or
这个 face 在这里是这么展示的
it's actually what happens to be the default our model is is
或者会展示默认的 model 表现的表情
that. Okay, so we need to, in all these segues, prepare
所以，我们需要给所有 segue 准备
the MVC that we are segueing to. We do that in the source
其需要展示的 model，我们在 segue 的源头设置
view controller, that is the emotions view controller.
在这里应该是 emotions 控制器
This is the thing that implements Prepare for Segue.
实现 prepareForSegue 这个方法
So I am just going to un comment out the comments here,
我要删掉这些注释
okay, for my Prepare for Segue. Make lots of space.
为 prepareForSegue 挪一些空间
Alright, so here we have Prepare for Segue,
在这里写上 prepareForSegue
we get the two arguments, the segue which tells us a little
我们需要两个参数，segue 参数告诉我们
bit about which segue it is and
这是哪个segue
what the destination view controller is and then we have
它的目的 controller 是哪一个
the sender. That's going to be those buttons,
还有一个 sender 参数，这应该是这些按钮
like the angry button, the mischievous button.
像是 angry button、mischievous button
That's what this is going to be,
这些应该就是这些控件
it's going to be the UI button. Okay?
像是 UIButton
This is any object because it is allowed to be any object.
这里必须是一些对象
In this case it's a button, but
在这种情况下，就是 button
it's allowed to be any object. All right.
但是，也可以允许是其他对象
So what do we do here in preparing for
我们在这里应该写些什么来为 segue 做准备呢？
segue? The first thing I'm going to do is get a hold
第一，我需要获取到
of the destination view controller, and
segue 目标 controller
make sure that it's a face view controller.
确保他是 face view controller
Cuz if it's not, I don't really know how to,
如果他不是的话，我确实不知道应该
the segue so I'm just going to do nothing in that case. So
怎么为这个 segue 做准备
to prepare for
在这种条件下
I'm going to create a little local variable, okay?
我需要创造一个局部变量
I'm going to call it destinationvc, destination
叫做 destinationvc
view controller. And that's just equal to the segue,
表示目的的 controller，这个等于
destin, segue, destinationViewController,
segue 的 destinationViewController
okay? Now this is a UIViewController, okay,
现在，这个就是一个 UIViewController
of some sort, it's some sub-class of UIViewController.
但是，应该是 UIViewController 的子类
I suppose it could even be UIViewController itself.
这应该就是 UIViewController 本身
There's probably a subclass of it, and so I need to get
这里应该用一个他的子类，所以我需要获得其子类
that subclass, I need to get this variable, in some way,
我需要让这个变量
so that it's a subclass of it. Or I can't work with it.
变为其子类
Right? Because, UIViewController, I wouldn't
要不然我不能将一些属于 faceViewController 的消息
be able to send any of the face view controller messages
传给他
to it, because it's just a generic UIViewController, so I
因为他只是一个通用的 UIViewController
need to get myself a faceview controller so I'm gonna say,
所以我需要得到一个 faceViewController
if I can let facevc, which is a new variable,
if let facevc
equal the destinationvc As a FaceViewController.
等于之前的变量 destinationvc 作为 FaceViewController
Then I'm ready to rock here. Okay, now I have
然后我准备在这里做操作
a FaceViewController, okay? So I've just casted.
现在，我通过转型获得了一个 FaceViewController
They're similar to how I can't work with any object,
这跟之前我不能做特殊操作的
I really can't work with a generic UIViewController.
通用 UIViewController 类似
I need the subclass. Otherwise how am I going to set its
我获得了他的子类，然后，
model, okay? I have to be able to talk to it. All right. So
接下来，我需要设置这个 controller 的 model
now I have this destination view controller.
现在我有了代表目标的 controller
Now I need the identifier. So here I'm gonna say, if I can
现在，我需要标识符
let the identifier equal the segue's identifier. Okay,
我需要让标识符等于 segue 的标识符
so here I'm just checking to make sure it's not nil.
这样写是为了检查确保它不为空
Now it should be angry, or mischievous, or happy.
他可以是 angry 、mischievous 或者是 happy
One of those identifiers that I put in the stored word,
可以是我之前设置的任何一个标识符，对吧？
right? And I could do something here like,
我应该写
switch on the identifier.
switch 标识符
And if it's angry then I'm going to have my face vc's
如果是 angry，我应该写让我的表情 controller
expression be a facial expression that's angry, blah,
表现生气的表情
blah, blah. I could do that but
blah，我可以这么写
that's going to be allot of if then, blah, blah, okay, mess.
但是，会是一些很乱的代码
So instead I'm going to do one of my favorite ways to
所以，相反的是，我会写一些我喜欢的
program, as you're probably getting the,
编程风格的代码，你可能已经想到了
idea about which is use a dictionary. Okay, so
对的，我们要用字典来表示
I have this dictionary I'm gonna type in real fast, okay,
我快速的写一下这些代码
and this dictionary has keys which are the identifiers, and
这些字典以这些标识符为键
it has values which are the appropriate facial expression.
对应的值为合适的 facial expression 模型
Okay, got that, so
明白了吗？
instead of doing all of this switching on the identifier
与在这里 switch 这些标识符相反的是
thing, I'm just going to say if I can let the expression
让 expression 变量等于我想要的
that I want equal these emotional faces up here.
facial expression 模型
Tha's this dictionary up here. Index by the identifier.
通过标识符来索引字典中的值
Okay? Then I know the expression that I want.
然后，我获得了对应的表情模型
And now I can prepare my face VC okay, by setting its
我可以为我要展示的 face VC 做准备
expression equal to this expression. Okay, and remember
让他的 expression 模型等于这个 expression
FaceVC.expression, that is just FaceViewControllers model
你记得吗? 在 FaceViewControllers 里它的模型是一个
which is a public bar. This View Controller allows
公共变量，它允许
its model to be set externally, publicly,
在外部设置其模型
okay, which makes sense given this kind of model.
这让我们可以在对应的地方设置其 model
Not all, and doesn't make sense always for
这样仅是在这个 viewcontroller 中
every MBC to allow it's model to be set but often it makes
设置其 model ，并不是所有viewcontroller 都可以设置
some sense. Alright, so now I've prepared this Faceview
现在我已经为这个 faceViewController 设置好了
controller to do what it needs to do. Everybody got that? OK.
它需要的东西，大家都明白吗？
So now let's run it and see if it's working. Okay.
现在我们运行一下，来看看是否正确显示
So here we go, we have our iPad here, let's try angry.
这是我们的模拟器 iPad，点击 angry
Crash a roo. Hmm. Wonder why that crashed? Well let's look,
哦，崩溃了，想一想为什么会崩溃呢？我们来检查下
let's use the debugger. Okay, we haven't used the debugger
我们需要用一下 debugger 模式，我们还没有
much in these demos but let's do it here. Seems like,
在这个 demo 中用过这个方法
okay, whenever I have a crash, I always look first in
不管什么时候，程序崩溃了，我总是先查看
the console, okay, because the console is always going to
控制台输出的信息，因为控制台总会告诉我一些
tell me something about what happened. And here it says
关于崩溃的信息，这里显示
unexpectedly found nil while unwrapping an optional value.
在解包一个可选值时，意外地发现了空异常
Okay, well this is probably the number one crasher you're
这种异常你可能经常获得
ever going to get, it's one of the few ways actually to crash
在 Swift 代码中，你可能经常
Swift code is to have unwrapping and nil.
在解包时，发现空异常
So it is happening on this orange line of code.
所以，在这一行，发生了这个异常
I am looking here. Does anyone see an optional here? No?
我看这一行，有人发现这里有可选值了吗？
Nobody sees an optional on this line of code?
没有人在这一行发现可选值吗？
It doesn't look like it, does it? Because you do not see any
这一行看上去没有可选值吗？
exclamation points. I am not unwrapping anything.
可能因为你没有看到感叹号，我没有解包任何值
What is going on? Well actually what is face view,
发生了什么呢？其实是这个 faceVIew
what's its type? Anyone remember? Our outlet,
它的类型有人记得吗？
that's our outlet remember here? Right, it's a optional
这是我们的 outlet，还记得吗？
face view, okay? It's implicitly unwrapped okay,
这是一个可选值得 faceView，他隐式解包了
but it's still an optional. And I told you in the slides,
但是他确实是一个可选值，ppt 里我说过
that your outlets are not set at the time you're preparing.
在你准备 segue 时，这些outlet还没有被设置
So this face view right here, okay, is nil, let's look.
所以，这里的 faceView 为空
Okay, here's where our variables are down here,
我们在这里可以看到这些变量
clicking on "self", face view, sure enough nil.
点击 self，faceView 确实为nil
So my pointer to my face view has not been set yet by iOS
在 iOS 中，这里的 faceView 还没有被设置
and that's always gonna be the case when you're preparing so
在你准备 segue 时，这种情形经常发生
be prepared for that happening okay. So what can we do about
所以，我们应该怎么做呢？
it here? Okay well one thing we could say if face view does
我们可以设置如果 faceView 不为空
not equal nil then we'll do all this updating UI stuff
我们来更新这些 UI
right? K, by the way why is this happening,
顺便说下，为什么会这样呢？
why are we on this line of code? If we look over here on
这行代码怎么了？
the left it'll show us how us we got here.
如果我们看左边的展示给我们的信息
Okay, so we're in this place right here,
然后再看对应的右边的代码
okay, and let's see how we got here by clicking here. See,
我们点击一下看看这是什么
we set our model which makes sense and it called up DUI, so
看，这里我们设置了我们的 model，然后更新了UI
why are we setting our model, okay, let's go up more. Sure
为什么会走这一行呢，我们朝上点
enough here we are preparing. Okay, setting our model.
因为在这里我们 prepare segue
So this is right, preparing for segway, goes in here set
然后设置了model
to our model. Wants to update UI, it's great.
设置了model 之后，更新UI
Unfortunately our view is not been connected via outlet.
不幸的是，这里我们的view没有连接 outlet
All right, so this is one way we could do it. By the way,
我们可以这样设置，避免他为空
there is another trickier way to do it which is to
顺便说一下，还有另一个复杂的方法处理这个问题
use question mark here.
在这里用问号
You know that question mark works for optional chaining,
你们知道在等号的右手边处理
right, on the right hand side of an equals?
用问号来处理可选链
It also works on the left hand side. If you put a question
在等号的左边也可以处理
mark there, that's and you can put as many of the question
你可以在等号的左边放置
marks as you want on the left side of an equals. And
你希望放置的任意的问号
if any of the things that you put a question mark are nil,
如果你在其后写问号的变量确实为空
it just ignores the whole statement.
他会忽略掉整个状态
Like it didn't even happen. Okay. So, that would be
就像没写这句话一样，这就是另一种方式了
another way. But we would have to put a question mark on
但是我们需要在这里的每一个 faceView
every single access of faceview in here. So,
后面都写上问号
we might as well just check to see if it's not nil. Now, is
所以，还不如我在上面检查一下 faceView 是否为空
this going to fix our problem? And the answer is, yes it is.
现在让我们看看这确实解决了我们的问题了没
Because we do update UI when our model gets set, but
确实解决了，因为在 model 被重新设置后需要更新UI
we also do update UI when this outlet gets set, remember?
我们需要在outlet被设置后，更新UI, 记得吗？
So when the outlet later, after the prepare is done,
所以，当outlet被设置后，准备好了
when the outlet comes along and gets set, boom,
outlet被设置了
our UI will get updated with the model that we set during
我们的 UI 界面被更新为我们设置的 model
prepare, okay? So it's going to work fine, okay?
这里就会正确运行，对吧？
But this is part of the reason why when our outlets get set,
这就是为什么我们设置了 outlet
we update UI and when our model gets set,
更新了UI 然后这时 model 才设置
we update our UI because the order of them happening can be
我们更新 UI，因为这两项发生的顺序
you know can vary. All right. Sound good alright.
有时候是不同的，看起来就应该这样
So we fixed that, we checked this so
现在我们解决了这个问题，我们来检查下
it's not gonna crash anymore, so let's run and
还会不会崩溃
hopefully this is all working like a charm now.
我们运行一下，希望一切正常
All right here we go ready? Angry,
现在看看对不对，Angry，
happy, worried, mischievous.
Okay. All right? So it's working great. Okay, and
运行起来很好
let's try it this way. Slide out. Angry, happy, right?
现在我们这么做，侧滑，Angry, happy
Working like a charm. Okay? Okay, all right.
看起来很好看，好的
Now, what about iPhone? Okay, this is great on iPad.
现在，在 iPhone 上是什么样子呢？在 iPad 上运行良好
Let's try running this on iPhone, and see what we get.
我们试着在 iPhone 上运行，看看是什么样
All right, here's our thing. We got it here. Let's try
好的，我们的模拟器在这里
happy. All right, we're happy! Actually, now we're not so
让我们尝试点击 happy，对的 happy
happy because we're stuck. Okay, there's no way for
事实上，我们没有很开心，因为我们卡住了
me to get back to choosing something else. Okay, I could
我没有办法返回去选择其他东西
try rotating. No. I can try sliding out from the left.
我尝试着旋转，不行，我从左边滑动
Nope, no. OK, split view does not split on an iPhone.
也不行，splitViewController 在 iPhone 上是不能分开的
Only on the iPhone 6 Plus, which is
只有在 iPhone 6 Plus 上可以运行
the only one big enough to really do it,
iPhone 6 Plus 是唯一一个够大的机型来展示 splitViewController
okay? So we're stuck here. So this UI that we have in our
所以，我们卡住了，在故事板中这套 UI 不能正常的运行在
storyboard is no good for iPhone, okay? Now we can still
iPhone里，我们现在仅仅可以
make our guy blink, okay? But that's all we can do.
设置小人眨眼，但是我们只能做着一件事
So unless we're happy just watching him blink all day
除非我们看着他光眨眼就满意了
we need to fix this. So how are we gonna make this work on
我们需要解决这个问题，怎么让这个功能在
iPhone? Okay. First we have to ask ourselves what would be
iPhone上也能正确运行呢？首先，我们需要思考
an appropriate UI on iPhone. Okay,
在 iPhone 上的合适 UI
and this is where navigation controller comes in.
这里就需要用到 navigationController 了
Navigation controller would be great here because
NavigationController 用在这里会很合适
you start the stack of cards with the angry mischievous
现在有一叠代表生气、淘气、担心的视图
worried MVC. And then when you click the face it puts
当你另外点击了一个 face ，它将
a new card on top which is the face. And then if
一个新的视图放在这个 face 之上
you want a different one you just hit back, throw that card
然后，如果你想换一个表情，你只需返回
away, and you are back to the angry mischievous worry choice
将之前的 face 扔掉，你就回到之前选择表情的视图了
again, right? Okay, so it's perfect, okay,
对吗？这样很好
navigation controller would be a perfect UI. So we need to
navigationController 是一个完美的 UI 控件
put navigation controller into our story board, okay. So
所以我们需要将 navigationController 放进故事板中
let's do that. Let's go back to our story board over here.
我们回到故事板
There's a lot of space here.
把编辑空间弄大一点
So where I'm gonna put this navigation controller? Well,
我应该把 navigationController 放哪儿呢？
you really need one navigation controller around the root.
我们确实应该一个根控制器外放置一个 navigationController
View controller. The base card, cards at the bottom.
这是最底下的 controller，在一叠 controller 下面
Okay? So I can put a navigation controller here in
我可以像放置其他控件那样，从这里取出控件，然后放置
the same way I put these other things by going down here. You
我可以这么放置 navigationController
can see there's a navigation controller right here.
你可以看到，这个就是 navigationController
I could drag it out. I could control, drag,
我可以把他拖出来，按住 control，然后 drag
etc. There's actually a cooler way to do it, which is select
确实还有更酷的方法来做这件事
your route MVC which is this guy. That's the card that's
先选中根控制器，就是这个
at the bottom of the stack and go up to editor and
这个就是一叠视图中最下面的那个
just like you did in bed and stack view, do embed and
然后选中 editor，就像把控件放进 stackView 中一样选中 embed in
negotiation controller. You can also do it for
然后选择 navigationController，你也可以通过这种方式
tab bar by the way, but do a navigation controller.
来添加 Tab Bar Controller，我们先选择 navigationController
Now watch what happens here, boom! You put this
看看发生了什么，boom！
inside a navigation control automatically wired it up.
这个控制器自动封装进了 navigationController
Now whats kind of interesting about this is, it also made
特别有趣的是，它会自动将
that navigation controller be the master of the split view.
navigationController 变为 splitView 中的 master
In other words, it kind of wrapped the navigation
换句话说，它将根控制器包裹进 navigationController
controller around the root con, the root view controller
而根控制器还保留了
and kept that pointer to the master. So
之前作为 master 的指针
now the master is actually a navigation controller,
所以，master 实际上就是一个 navigationController
with this as it's root view controller. Still all these
这个控制器作为根控制器
segways are still here. Okay, these segues are still,
而且还保留着这些 segues
they didn't it didn't undo any of these segues. And
这些 segues 并没有被撤销
this is still the detail of the split-view controller.
这个控制器还是原来split-view controller 中的 detail
>> How did I put it in there?
I selected this, which is my root-view-controller,
我选中根控制器
and I went to editor, embed in, navigation controller.
然后选择 editor -> embed in -> navigationController
Okay? So, now this is an interesting set up right here.
做这些挺有意思的
Let's see if just fixed it, maybe it will just work.
现在，看看刚刚做的有没有起作用
Because, you know, I hear,
因为，你知道的
I got this, in a navigational controller, right now, so
我刚刚得到了一个 navigationController
it should just work on a iPhone, right?
他会不会只在 iPhone 中生效呢？
Let's try it. How many people think this going to work?
有多少人认为会起作用？
Raise your hand if you think this is going to work.
如果你觉得会起作用，请举起手
Nobody thinks it's gonna work. It is going to work! Gotcha.
没有人觉得这会起作用吗，事实上，会起作用的！
Okay. So here I am in my navigation controller.
现在我看到的是 navigationController
I'm going to go back. Here is my stuff. Let us try worried.
点击返回，这是选择表情的，点击担心的
He looks worried. I am not worried though cuz I know it
确实看起来很担心，我倒不会再担心了
is going to work. Okay so this worked fine, exactly what
因为我知道这起作用了
we want on iPhone. Now my question to you is,
iPhone 上运行良好，我的问题来了
is this still going to work on iPad? Okay.
在 iPad 上会起作用吗？
Let's go look at that. Let's go back to iPad.
我们来看看在 iPad 上
How many people think it's going to work on iPad still.
有多少人觉得在 iPad 上也会同样起作用呢？
One. Two. Three. You guys are getting smart. Yes.
一，二，三，你们变聪明啦
It's still going to work on iPad.
是的！在 iPad 上也会起作用
Okay. It's pretty cool the way they made this work so you can
只在一个故事板中构建页面，但是能运行在
build one storyboard that'll work fine on both platforms.
不同的平台上，确实是一件很酷的事情
So here we go, this is iPad, we can turn it around,
现在，这是 iPad，转过来
here it is, it is in a navigation controller,
页面在一个 navigationController 中
you see? Which is actually kind of nice, cuz I can put
你们看到了没？这样确实很好
a nice title in here for this MBC, okay. But when I click in
因为我可以在这上面写一个标题
here, it's not going to slide a deck onto the deck of cards,
当我点击时，这个视图并不会侧滑出视线
it's going to do the show detail, right, angry, happy,
它会正确显示 detail ，生气的、高兴的
worried, mischievous. Okay? Everyone got that,
担心的、淘气的，对吗？大家明白
how we do that? Now this kind of structure,
我们怎么做了吗?这是一种结构
we have split view, navigation controller, and
我们先有 splitViewController, navigationController
then the content for your master, and
然后是 master 的内容
then the detail right here. Very common to build this,
然后是 detail 的内容，这是通常的做法
because if you're building an app that works on both,
因为，如果你在做一个app，这是常规的做法
this is what it's gonna look like basically. All right,
这是非常基本的操作
so I'm gonna show you one
现在，我要向你展示
last thing here of interest, which is these titles, okay.
这里最后一个有趣的点，就是标题
So we have this little space for a title up here, so
我们这里给标题留了一个小空间
I'd like to put a title here, okay. And how do I put a title
我要在这儿放置标题，我怎么在这儿放标题呢？
up here? Again, remember that's object oriented, okay.
记住，这一切都是面向对象的
That title comes from whatever MVC happens to be showing in
这些标题会在 navigationController
this navigation controller at the time. So
展现MVC 的时候出现
I go to the storyboard, to that MVC, which is this one,
我打开故事板，选择这个 MVC
and could just double click on it, okay? So
双击一下，对吗？
we'll call this one Emotions, okay. So now if I run,
标题叫做 Emotions ，如果我运行下
I get a nice title up here,
我得到一个很好地标题 Emotions
Emotions. What if I wanted a title over here? Okay,
如果这里也想有个标题呢？
how would I do it if I wanted a title over here?
如果这个位置也想有标题，我应该怎么做呢？
Well if you look on the iPhone,
你看在 iPhone 中
okay if we go back and oops, run this on iPhone.
返回，要运行在 iPhone中
Since both MVCs are in that navigation controller,
因为这些 MVC 都在navigation controller
they both have titles Okay, so if I go here, here's emotions,
所以他们都有标题，这里有标题emotions
angry. Look, there's room for a title up here. But
这里也有标题
back on the iPad, that's not the case because the detail,
但是，回到 iPad 上，这里就没有标题了
when you replace the detail it doesn't actually put it
因为，在 iPad上，当你换到 detail 页面时
inside the same navigation controller that the master is
detail 并没有被包裹进 master 在的那个 navigationController
in. So the master is in a navigation controller, but
所以，master 在 navigationController 中
this is not. So if we wanted a title here,
而 detail 并不在，所以如果我们想要设置标题
we have to put this guy in a navigation controller.
我们就需要把 detail 放进 navigationController里
Even though we're not going to use the navigation controller
如果我们就是想用 navigationController 来展示个标题
for anything except for the title on the split view case.
并不做其他事情，在 splitViewController 里
We would still have to do it.
我们还得用 navigationController 来做
And in fact, iOS makes it so that just works, okay?
事实上， iOS 就是这么设计的
So I'm going to go here. Down to this guy. Okay and
所以，点击这个 controller
I'm going to embed him in a navigation controller okay.
把他包裹进一个 navigationController
So just have this, I have the face selected,
就这么做，点击一个表情
embed puts him in there, okay. Now this
把他放进了一个 navigationController 里
almost is going to work, okay, if we look at what this looks
如果我们运行看看这样设置是什么样的
like. Okay? There's a little bit of an issue here because
可能是运行正常，可能有一些问题
these segues are now going to this navigation controller.
因为这些 segues 现在开始指向 navigationController
But let's take a look at what it looks like anyway. Okay,
我们还是看一下到底运行的怎么样吧
on iPad look, they're both in navigation controller.
在 iPad 上，确实都在 navigation controller 里
So I've room for a title here now, okay? And if I click,
我挪点空间来看看
it doesn't work anymore. Okay, so I broke it by putting this
如果我点击了，这个表情并没有真正展现
in a navigation controller. Now why, and by the way,
当我把它放置在 navigation controller 里了，反而破坏了这个表情
does it work on iPhone? Yes, still works on iPhone. So
顺便看一下，在 iPhone 中正常吗？看起来很正常
it did not break it on iPhone because iOS is smart
它没有破坏在 iPhone 上的显示，因为 iOS系统够聪明
enough to know this is already in a navigation controller, so
它知道这个控制器已经在 navigation controller 里了
I'm just gonna ignore this navigation controller and
所以在展示它时，会忽略它自己的那个 navigation controller了
put this in here. See? So this looks the same, no change,
看到了吗？这看起来没啥不一样的
still in a navigation controller.
仍然在 navigation controller 中
iOS didn't put a navigation controller inside a navigation
iOS 不会将一个 navigation controller 放在另一个 navigation controller 里
controller, in fact iOS never puts a navigation controller
事实上，iOS 永远都不会将一个 navigation controller
inside another one. Okay, if it sees and
放在另一个 navigation controller 里
encounters another one, it just ignores that one,
如果它发现它包裹在另一个 navigation controller 里，它会自动忽略它
okay. It's like you're either in one or you're not,
你可以把它放进一个 navigation controller 之中或者不放
you can't be in two at the same time. So
但是你不能同时包裹两个 navigation controller
it worked great on the iPhone. So why did it break though?
所以，在 iPhone 中运行良好，但是，为什么崩溃了呢？
Sorry, it worked great visually but it still,
它看起来运行良好，但是
I didn't show it there but it didn't work to click.
在点击时，运行的并不良好
Okay, just like in the iPad it didn't work to click. And
跟在 iPad 里一样，点击后效果不对
why didn't it work to click? Well, we have to understand or
为什么点击的效果不对呢，这里我们必须了解或者
prepare a little bit better there, okay?
准备了这点知识
And in fact, let's take the time to do this.
事实上，会耗费我们一点时间来说明这个问题
I'm gonna go in the debugger and show you this.
我将在 debugger 模式下说明这个问题
So I'm gonna set a break point right here, okay?
我需要在这里打个断点
In prepareForSegue because prepareForSegue is not
在 prepareForSegue 这个方法里打断点
properly preparing that thing. So let's see why it's failing.
因为它没有很好地为这个 segue 做准备，我们来看看为什么失败了
All right, so here we go. I'm going to hit happy. And
我们准备好了，运行，点击 happy
it's going to break, okay, at this prepare.
到断点这里了，在 prepareForSegue 里面
So it's trying to prepare that thing to be happy. And
所以，它准备为展示 happy 做一些事
what is, let's look at this destination VC right here.
在这里看看 destinationVC
Look what its type is. It's a UN navigation controller.
看看它的类型是什么，这是个 UINavigationController
And that kind of makes sense, right?
这说明了一些问题，是吗？
Because if you look at our storyboard,
因为在 storyboard 中
these segues are going down to this navigation controller.
这些 segue 指向这些 navigation controller了
Okay? So that's just a little bit of a twist.
所以这看起来有点纠结
A little bit tricky. And all we have to do is look at this
有点复杂，我们需要判断这个 destinationvc
destination VC and if it's a navigation controller,
如果他是一个 navigation controller
then let's get moving inside of it. Okay. And
我们需要获得它里面包裹的东西
work on that. Okay. So I'm just going to say here,
让我们这样做吧，我得在这里说明
if I can let Navcon, which is a local variable,
写一个局部变量，navcon
equal the destination VC as a UI navigation controller. So,
如果将 destinationvc 作为一个 UINavigationController 赋值给 navcon
if the destination happens to be UINavigationController,
如果 destinationvc 确实就是一个 UINavigationController
then I'm gonna let I'm just gonna set the destination VC
我将这个 destinationvc 等于这个
equal to the navcon.visibleViewController.
navcon 的 visibleViewController
Which is optional, so I'm gonna,
这是一个可选值，我打算
actually I won't even unwrap it.
事实上，我不是要将它解包
I'm gonna say if it's visible view control and
而是，如果它就是一个 visibleViewController
if the navigation control doesn't have a visible view
或者这个 navigationController 没有 visibleViewController
control then we'll just leave it to be the destination view
它会直接赋值为自身
controller. This'll have to be bar. Okay? So
这样做更保险，是吗？
here all I'm doing is, I'm just saying if I'm preparing
我要写的就是这些，如果在准备这个 segue 时
to segue to something and it's a navigation controller,
它是一个 navigationController
then instead look inside the navigation controller and
我会获取到 navigationController 里面的东西
segue to that instead. Okay? Prepare that instead. Okay?
segue 会指向里面的 controller ，为展示这个做准备，是吗？
Everyone understand what I'm doing there with these, this
大家都明白我在这里写了什么吗？
little Three lines of code? >> [INAUDIBLE]
明白我写的这三行代码吗？
>> Yes, so you're
对，你说
saying, could I go
我能不能
back here in the storyboard and
在 storyboard 做我刚刚写下的操作
have all these segue things go down over this way instead?
将这些 segue 直接指向展示的 controller？
You wouldn't actually want that,
事实上，你不会想这么做的
because when the segue creates the MVC that it's gonna show,
因为当 segue 创造的这些 MVC 准备去展示时
you want it to create a navigation controller. So
你希望他在一个 navigationController 里
you actually want it to go into this navigation.
所以你希望在一个 navigationController 里看到那个 controller
It's just that, when it comes to preparing it, you don't
这样当你准备展示它时
really want to prepare the navigation controller,
你不是想为展示那个 navigationController 做准备
you wanna prepare the thing inside. So
而是为 navigationController 里面的东西做准备
that's why we're in this code just looking inside
这就是为什么我们在这些代码里
the navigation controller to make the destination
将 destinationvc 赋值为 navigationController 里包裹的东西
that we're preparing be the thing inside. Okay?
我们为里面的东西做准备，对吗？
So little trickiness. You'll often have this little code.
有一点点难，你会经常写这种代码
I'll actually show you later in the quarter kind of
事实上，一会儿我会用
a little more sophisticated way to put this in there.
一个更常用的方法来设置这个
You can put it there with one syntactical element,
你可以用一个更语义性的元素
it's possible, but this I want to leave explicitly so
但是，我想更明确的设置这个
you understand what's going on here. So now when we run it's
你也会明白这里做了什么，现在，我们运行一下
going to work because when we segue to something
看看是否工作，因为我们在这里将 segue 指向了
that's navigation controls, it can look inside. See, angry,
navigationController 里面的东西
happy, worried, mischievous. And the last thing I wanna do
看看， angry、happy、worried、mischievous 都正确的展示了
is set this title right here. Now this title was fixed.
我需要做的最后一件事就是设置 controller 的标题
This is always the emotions MVC.
这需要在展示表情的 MVC 里设置标题
But this MVC, its title kinda depends on what it's showing
但是这个 MVC，它的标题像是需要在展示它的地方来设置
here, doesn't it? Alright like if we are showing angry it
是这样吗？就像是，如果我们要展示 angry
would be nice if this title would be angry.
它的标题就是 angry，这样应该很不错
It would be nice if this title were worried.
展示 worried 时，它的标题就是 worried
Okay? So where can we get the appropriate title here?
所以，我们得在哪里获得这个对应的标题呢？
we'll we can get it form the button that's asking us
我们可以从引发 segue 的按钮那里获得标题
to segue. Right? If this angry button asks us to segue then
对吗？如果是这个 angry 按钮让我们来展示表情
let's set this title to be the title of the angry button.
我们就将标题设置为这个 angry 按钮的标题
Right? So, looking back here, in our "prepareForSegue".
对吗？回到 prepareForSegue 这里
Is that title of the angry button available to us here?
我们可以用 angry 按钮的标题吗？
Where? Where can I get it? From "sender", yeah, exactly.
在哪里，在哪里我能获得这个标题呢？ sender！
Okay. You guys are getting it. That's really good.
对的，你们已经明白这一点了，很好
Sender is the button that's causing the segue to happen.
Sender 就是那个引发 segue 的按钮
That's gonna be the angry button. So, it's any object.
这应该就是那个 angry 按钮，这可以是任何对象
So I'm gonna have to cast it to be a button. But that's no
所以，我想让它转型为一个 button，这没什么问题
problem. I'm just gonna say if I can let the sending button
我要写如果我让 sending button 作为一个 UIButton
equal the sender as a UI button, okay? And
等于 sender，对吗？
if not, if I'm segueing from code or something here,
如果它不能转为一个UIButton，或者我是用代码
then this is not gonna work.
或者其他方法引发的 segue ，这样就不能正常工作了
But so what. Okay? We just won't get the title we want.
我们就不能给 Face View Controller
On our Face View Controller. But if it is then I can just
获取到我们想要的标题，如果能转为 UIButton
set the Face View Controllers navigation item. Does everyone
我可以设置给 Face View Controller 设置它的 navigation item
remember what navigation item is? It's kind of just a bundle
大家都记得 navigation item 吗？他就像一捆东西
of things like a little bag of goodies that the navigation
像是 navigation controller 在展示它里面的 MVC时
controller looks inside of when that MVC is showing.
navigationController 有的一袋东西
To get information like the buttons or the title, okay.
为了得到这个 button 的属性，比如 title
Equals the sending button's current title,
等于这个触发 button 的当前标题
okay. So this little bag of goodies, navigation item,
我们在文档中看一下
here let's look at it in the documentation, okay.
这一袋 navigationItem 里的东西
I'm going to go here. The I View Controller,
我要打开这个，这是 ViewController
it's like a navigation item.
这是那些 navigationItem
You can see it house things like the title to show
你可以在目录里看到 title
when this MVC is showing in the navigation controller.
当 MVC 在 navigationController 中展示时
Back bar button item to use instead of the default one.
Back bar button item 就是默认的
Left bar button items and right bar button items.
Left bar button item 和 right bar button item
You can put you know things on the top, left and right.
你可以将你获得的东西放在上面，左面或者右面
That's what's in this little bag of goodies. And
这就是这一袋东西里面的
this bag of goodie is only looked in when you are on top
这一袋东西只会在
the of a navigation controller stack.
navigationController 堆中最上面展示
All right, so let's see if that works.
好的，让我们看看是否有用
All right, here we go. Let's try angry,
运行一下，我们来点击 angry
there it is, angry, happy, worried, mischievous. Okay,
这里的标题有 angry, happy, worried, mischievous
and let's make sure that it's working on iPhone.
让我确认在 iPhone 中是否运行良好
All right, let's go back here. Angry. Yes.
好的，让我们回到这里，angry
Look he even got the title right. Happy.
看起来我们正确的设置了标题
That's definitely happy. Worried. Okay?
happy，这确确实实是 happy，worried
All right, everyone got that? So this is how we can build
好的，大家都明白了吗？这就是怎样
these nice apps that work on both platforms, okay? They
做一个 app 可以适配各个平台，对吗？
work in split views. They work in navigation controllers.
这是在 split view 里的，它们都在 navigationController 里面
Now if you were building an iPhone only app, you could do
如果你只是做一个 iPhone 的 app
this exact same thing but you wouldn't need the split view.
你可以不用 splitView 就完成同样的事情
You could just take this view and
move your start Your little starting arrow right here.
You just move right up here to this navigation controller,
and you wouldn't need this navigation controller either,
okay, because you don't have this issue where this whole
thing is in a separate space like it is on iPad and iPhone.
They'd all be inside the navigation controller.
Okay? Now not surprisingly for you're homework I'm going to
ask you to do pretty much exactly this. Okay?
You're going to have a calculator.
You're going to have a calculator graph,
have to write the code for. So you're going to have two MVC's
which you're going to
and you're going to have to put it in the situation like
this that works on both iPad and iPhone. Okay?
And now you know how to do it. All right back to the slides.
Okay the View Controller Lifecycle.
So I've been mentioning this and we delete
those methods in there for the View Controller Lifecycle. So
now let's talk about what this View Controller Lifecycle is.
So View Controller Lifecycle It's really just a set of
methods that gets sent to your view controller as your
view controller goes through it's lifetime. Okay,
meaning it's lifetime is it gets created, it does things,
it dies. Okay, and as it goes through that life,
you get sent these nice messages. Okay? So the start
of the lifecycle is obviously the creation of your MVC. And
MVCs are almost always created out of storyboards I'd say 99%
of the time okay? That's how you've seen us do it and
that's how it's done, okay? It can be done in code but
I'm not even gonna show you how to do that in this course,
It's rarely done, okay?
The great thing about putting in a storyboard is that people
looking at your code can see what you intend visually,
okay? In terms of your MVC and
their layout and their segways to each other. So
that's why we try to do stuff in the storyboard. So 99% of
the time these MVCs are being created out of the storyboard.
After they're created they go through the following steps,
one they get prepared okay,
they get segwayed too they get prepared so that first.
Then outlet setting happens that's why we had that crusher
because outlet setting happens after prepare.
Then they appear and disappear. Okay,
now this can happen over and over. This thing is gonna
appear on screen, go away, appear on screen, go away. For
example, when we had the iPad version of our demo here, and
I would pull out the master, and then I would hide it, and
I'd pull out the master, and then I would hide it.
Okay, it was appearing and disappearing. Alright?
Then as this is all happening, geometry changes can happen to
this thing, mostly due to rotation from
portrait to landscape, changes the geometry. And then,
very rarely you can get into a low memory situation
where your view controller may be asked to participate in
freeing up some memory, super rare.
Alright So let's talk about all these methods, okay?
After instantiation and preparation and
outlet-setting, you get a very important method sent to you
called viewDidLoad. Okay Load refers to loading up your
outlets, okay? So viewDidLoad is an awesome place to put
initialization code in your I view controller.
It's why you almost never have to override View controller's
init method. Okay it has a very strange init method.
You don't even wanna think about it's so weird.
Okay? But luckily you never need to override because you
got viewDidLoad. Okay? You put all your initialization code
almost all into viewDidLoad, okay,
it's kind of like your init for view controllers,
it's awesome. And it's great there because you're prepared,
and your outlets are set. So it's like, whoa,
you are ready to really get initialized, okay, and
of course all your instance variables are initialize,
or you wouldn't exist, okay? One really good thing to do
here is to update your UI, so you notice we had update UI in
the outlet setter property observer for
face view, okay? More likely you'd put update UI
in your viewDidLoad, okay. Cuz you know by viewDidLoad,
everything is ready to be updated.
Okay, now you're still gonna want it in your models,
didSet, because someone might change your model after
you've been loaded, okay?
But no one's going to change your outlets after you've been
loaded, your outlets get set up and now you own them, okay?
So they're, no one's gonna set it to point to something else,
okay? Now one thing to be careful about viewDidLoad,
though, is geometry, okay? The geometry of your view is
still probably the square, okay, of your storyboard. So
it's useless to do any calculations in viewDidLoad,
that have anything to do with your geometry.
If you're looking at your bounds and trying to make
a calculation is a waste of time, because it's a square.
It's not, it hasn't been updated to the portrait or
landscape of the device you're running on. Okay,
so this is the one think you don't do in viewDidLoad.
The other thing I wouldn't do in viewDidLoad is
anything that's going to kick off something expensive, okay?
Computing expensive or network intensive, whatever.
There's a better place to do that.
That's because viewDidLoad, kay,
your view controller got created. There's,
it's not a 100% guarantee it's gonna appear onscreen.
It might or might not. Depends on what the user touches in
your UI. So you wouldn't wanna kick off something expensive
until you know you're gonna be onscreen. And that brings us
to viewWillAppear, kay? So, viewWillAppear is called right
before you get put onscreen. So you are sure when this is
called that you're going to be put onscreen.
This is a great place to start something expensive.
Now you're gonna learn starting next week that iOS
apps, you wanna build them multi-threaded, okay?
Multi-threaded means, you're gonna have multiple things
going on at the same time in your app. They'll be sharing
the processor, time sharing the processor basically,
unless you have multi-core I guess,
which I guess that's formed is a basically running multiple
things at the same time. Your UIs gonna be running in one
thread at a very high priority and then other things
like accessing the network or things that block, things that
take a long time, we are gonna be running another thread.
And we are gonna be running simultaneously,
because we never want our UI to be blocked. Okay,
when user touches on something it should immediately respond.
I don't care what you're doing. Okay, you don't wanna
touch on something and it does nothing, because you're out
trying to fetch something from the network and
the network is slow. That would be a nightmare,
okay? So viewWillAppear is we would, you
would fire off another thread to go do something expensive.
kay, now your view is going to instantly appear on
screen without that data that you tried to get,
or whatever the expensive thing is.
So you have to learn to program in iOS, so
that multi-threading works.
And mostly that's a matter of putting UIs on the screen
that might not have all the information yet. Okay,
they might be fetching some data from the network so they
have a little spinning wheel or something loading dot,
dot, [LAUGH] dot. Something that tells the user, yeah,
I know you wanna see this data. I'm working on it, but
it has to come on screen instantly, okay?
You can't block, wait to get you one and then come on.
It's just, you can't do that, it doesn't work especially
iOS. Like the network can be really slow and
it might be stall. All right, cell network can be super
slow, so you can't do that. So the viewWillAppear
is a good place to kick off that kind of stuff.
Now, geometry is more likely to be correct here,
because you are just about to come on screen. But,
I still wouldn't put geometry calculations in here.
There is a better place for
that as well. There is also a viewDidAppear.
This gets sent right after you have come on screen.
This is a good place to do things like start
an animation. Okay, cause now you know you're onscreen,
boom, you can start an animation or something like
that. Okay, similarly there's viewWillDisappear, okay
usually viewWillDisappear, you're going to undue
the things you did in view will appear, so here you might
stop your animation. Or stop looking at the gyro, okay,
because things, things are going to disappear, so
there's no point in looking at the gyro anymore And there is
also a viewDidDisappear. Okay. This is where you might free
up something you fetched from the network in viewWillAppear.
See how they kind of a mirror each other, the will did
appear and then they will and did disappear. Kinda do and
undo things as it goes on and off, and these appear and
disappear could be viewDidLoad is only called once.
Okay one time. This could be called repeatedly as your view
controller comes on and off screen, appears it disappears,
appears it disappears, so this could be called repeatedly,
okay. So you wouldn't wanna do something in here
like if you're gonna fire off a fetch on the network
that's expensive, you wouldn't wanna be doing it over and
over if you already have the information from the last time
it appeared. Kay, so be a little careful about that. So
if the geometry, if you wanna do something based in
geometry, where do you do that? Well,
there's lifecycle methods specifically for
that, viewWillLayoutSubviews and viewDidLayoutSubviews. So
every time your bounds changes and sometimes when it doesn't
change, be careful, you'll get these two messages.
ViewWillLayoutSubviews and viewDidLayoutSubviews. Yeah.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Great question, so
the question is, would my bounds change if for example,
I added a navigation bar at the top or
maybe the tab bar at appeared in the tab bar or
I'm in the split view? And I appeared on the other side,
in other words, can it change due to the environment I'm in?
And the answer is, it can,
now it doesn't usually change with the navigation case,
because action that navigation bar is layered on top of
your view, it's kinda semi see through, if you look. If you
go look at navigation items,in the navigation bars, they're
actually kind of translucent and the thing is behind it, so
your bounds actually wouldn't probably change there.
But they might change if you're put into a tab bar,
because that space at the bottom might not overlap.
Okay, but the main time your balance changes when you
rotate, but it can happen other times too.
So between viewWillLayoutSubviews and
viewDidLayoutSubviews all that auto layout is gonna happen,
the stuff based on the constraints.
Remember all that blue dash lines and all that stuff?
That's gonna happen between.
So you can do stuff before all the blue lines, the autolayout
stuff is happening, or you can do it after, okay?
You rarely need to do anything here,
because usually the constraints are making all
the decisions about what to do with everything, okay? But
it is possible sometimes, you know, not in assignment three,
maybe in assignment six in this class. Maybe you might
wanna do something in viewWill or DidLayoutSubviews. But this
is the only place you wanna do anything that's geometry
dependent, okay? Yeah, one thing about these methods,
don't think that these are only gonna
be called when you're bound to actually changes.
The system is allowed to call these any time it wants, and
sometimes it might be drawing something to an offscreen
buffer to prepare to do an animation and so
it calls this, okay? But, and
then it actually draws on the screen and calls it again.
And the bounds have not actually changed, okay? So
don't expect that every single time this calls the bounds
will be different. If you do something really expensive as
a result of a bounds change, you might wanna keep track of
what the bounds were the last time you did that expensive
thing. And when this gets called,
make sure the bounds have actually changed, okay?
Again, you're not gonna need any of this for
assignment three, but it's good to know.
This can be recalled all the time, repeatedly, over and
over. Even if your bounds have not actually changed. Okay, so
auto rotation. Usually what happens in auto rotation.
When auto rotation is when you turn your phone from landscape
to portrait, it automatically changes your bounds to be tall
and skinny. And then wide and short, okay?
So autorotation is usually just a bounds change, so
you're just dealing with it in view did layout sub views, or
more likely, you just have constraints, and
the constraints just work, okay? So
there's really nothing to do, but it is possible to
get involved in autorotation, specifically in the animation.
If you watch an autorotation really, really closely,
you'll see that the views actually move. They move from
their position in portrait to where they are in landscape
in an animated fashion. They don't just jump there,
they kind of fly across the screen. And you can fly things
across the screen, too, if you want using this,
life cycle method called will, viewWillTransitionToSize. And
it's basically telling you, this is going to transition.
It has this thing called a transition coordinator.
You can look up the documentation on it. But
the main thing the transition coordinator has is a closure
that you can provide that will be executed alongside
the animation that it's doing to animate your,
your, rotation, okay? You won't need this in this class,
but I just wanna let you know this is here. Okay,
in low-memory situations, didReceiveMemoryWarning, okay,
this is only gonna happen if your app uses a lot of memory,
okay? iPhones today have so much memory,
it's ridiculous, okay?
So this is not really gonna happen, likely. But if you had
a memory leak where you're leaking videos in memory,
or images, huge images, or
something like that, it's possible you might get this.
When you get this, you should throw out any pointers to big
things you have in the heap that you can recreate, okay?
So you can re-download them from the web or
from your file system or something.
You should throw them out when you get this one. Okay,
going back to the very beginning of the lifecycle,
there's another interesting method called awakeFromNib.
Okay, awakeFromNib is sent to you really early before
preparation, before outlet setting, before all that, but
only if you're coming out of a storyboard. Okay, so it's this
really, really, really, really early method that gets called.
And it actually gets sent to every object that comes out of
a storyboard, not just view controllers,
okay? Now I mention it at the end here,
because I really don't want you using it that much, okay?
You're much better off putting things in viewDidLoad,
viewWillAppear, those kind of places than awakeFromNib,
okay? Some people find out about this, and they just put
all of their initialization junk into awakeFromNib, and
it's not really for that. It's for
really kind of exceptional circumstances,
where you really, really early you need to do something for
some reason, okay? Set, you're gonna need to set yourself
as a controller of some other object that something's
happening early, whatever. But I just wanna let you know it's
in there. Okay, so here's the summary of the lifecycle.
You're instantiated, usually from your storyboard.
awakeFromNib is then called.
Segue prep happens if you're being segued to,
which you almost always are when MVCs are being created.
It's because you're being segued to usually. Then
your outlets get set, okay, the things like display and
the calculator get set. Then viewDidLoad gets called, and
you can do a lot of nice initialization here that's not
geometry related. Then viewWillAppear and, and
DidAppear and then viewWillDisappear and
viewDidDisappear will be sent to you as you appear and
disappear on screen. Meanwhile, at any time,
whether you are onscreen or not,
whether you've appeared or not,
you can be set viewWillLayoutSubviews and
viewDidLayoutSubviews. Okay, and that's where you're going
to react to geometry changes if nec, if you need to outside
of constraints. Okay, usually constraints will just do it
for you. And if your memory gets
low at any time, you could get didReceiveMemoryWarning.
If you get didReceiveMemoryWarning and
you don't clean up your memory,
the system will probably kill you, okay? Just probably
your app will appear to crash to the user. Okay, so
I have a short demo here for View Controller Lifecycle,
and I'm just gonna throw some print statements into all of
those Lifecycle methods. Okay, that's all I'm gonna do. And
then we're gonna run our FaceIt, and we're gonna see,
as view controllers appear and disappear and
get created, what's happening in the Lifecycle,
okay? So that's all this demo is,
it's very brief. Okay, the way that I'm going to,
kind of print in the console is I have this, a little
extension here called, VCL, View Controller Lifecycle,
then I'm just gonna add to FaceIt, copy it in, and
I will post this, so you can look at it if you want.
But it's basically, it's just extending these classes to
override all of these, things. And
one thing that's cool is it will show you, the log which
instance of the Face View Controller, which instance of
the emotion controller, okay? So, that's kind of fun.
All right, so let's go ahead and run this, let's do it on,
iPhone first. All right, so this thing appeared,
all right, and it's showing the face, okay, this is kind
of like on the iPad, it would be showing the detail here.
It's showing a face, but we haven't chosen an emotion. And
let's look over here what happened. Both an Emotions
view controller and a Face view controller have been
created and instantiated, okay? Now that's because
the Emotion view controller is at the bottom of the stack and
a Face view controller is on top of it.
So they're both on the stack, that means they both exist.
However, notice that while the Emotions 1 has had viewDidLoad
called, because its outlets have all been set and
all that stuff, it has never appeared.
You see Emotions 1 never gets viewWillAppear,
because it never has appeared. We've never seen the angry,
mischievous, that has not appeared on screen. So
it hasn't appeared, whereas the Face 1 has, so
it's gotten viewWillAppear. It got, it laid out, okay,
viewWillLayoutSubviews and DidLayoutSubviews.
And then it got viewDidAppear, and sure enough,
here it is. Now I'm gonna press Back, the Back button,
and let's watch what happens, okay?
Face 1 got viewWillDisappear because of course,
it was gonna disappear. Emotions 1, that's this one,
got viewWillAppear cuz it's about to appear.
Then Emotions 1 got laid out a couple of times here.
Let's see some more here, there we go. Okay,
so Emotions 1 got laid out a couple of times here,
see if you will ask at the same exact size. So this
is why I'm saying be careful, that can happen multiple
times. Why might that happen? Again, maybe the system was
preparing to animate that thing sliding in, and
so it was drawing off screen, then it was drawing on screen,
and it was laying out both times,
it's called it both times. You don't know why,
you don't care why. You just have to be prepared for
the fact that it could call it multiple times. Then Face
1 got viewDidDisappear because the face disappeared,
it slid off. And Emotions 1 got viewDidAppear, because it
got replaced on top of it. Then notice Emotions 1 got lay
out again. Okay, even though it was already on screen.
Why, I don't know. Maybe this is the layout for
it actually appearing on screen. It's not clear. Okay,
everybody got that? Now I'm gonna click on one of these,
I'm gonna click on Happy, and let's watch what happens.
Okay, now most important thing to watch here, okay, is that
Face 1, that first face that we showed up is gone, see?
No more reference to Face 1. It has created a new face,
came out of the story board. Okay, this is what I'm talking
about. When you segue, it creates a new NVC.
That first Face 1 is out of the heap, it is gone, okay?
Every time you segue, you get a new one. But Emotions, okay?
The root, it's still Emotions 1, okay?
Since it sits on the root, the base of the card stack,
it never comes off. So, it just sits there forever, okay?
New cards come on and off, on and off.
But it's at the root, so it just sits there. So
it's always gonna be Emotions 1, okay? And then, again you
can see it goes through willDidLoad, viewWillAppear,
got laid out, Face 2 finally did appear, okay? And notice
that Emotions 1 did disappear because it got covered up
by this one. Okay, again if we go back and
I click a different one like Mischievous,
now we have Face 3, okay? Face 2 is gone forever but
still Emotions 1. Everyone understand that?
Okay, now let's run this on the iPad.
Okay, so here, okay, we're seeing the detail, okay?
Notice here that even though the master does not appear
on screen, it gets created. Not only does it get created,
it gets laid out. But it never got viewWillAppear and
viewDidAppear, because the master has never appeared,
okay? Whereas Face 1, it did get appear, and it appeared,
Now watch what happens if I rotate, okay, I'm gonna rotate
right?
to landscape. Okay, now when I rotate to landscape,
all of a sudden the master, Emotions 1, it got that
viewWillTransitionToSize thing.
That's the auto rotation thing I was telling you about, okay?
And Emotions 1 also got laid out and
told it would appear, and then it did appear, okay? Now Face
1 also got to participate in that rotation. See,
animatingAlongsideTransition. Okay, and
then here's Emotion 1 appear. Notice that inside here, okay,
there's no viewWillAppear or viewWillDisappear for Face 1.
That's cuz it was already on screen,
okay, so even though its bounds changed, okay, and
it got viewWillLayoutSubviews, it never got viewWillAppear,
it already was on screen. That make sense?
And now interesting. I'm gonna click on one of these, and
what's gonna happen to Face 1? Out of the heap. Okay,
watch this. Angry, see Face 1 gone, now we're on Face 2.
So even in a split view where it seems like,
you know with the cards, it's really obvious that yeah,
I'm throwing the card away, I'm making a new card. But
even here in a split view,
I'm throwing away the detail,
I'm making a new one. Plopping it right in on top, okay?
So all of these segues create a new MVC, even if they're
a split view navigation controller, whatever.
The only ones that don't that you've seen is in tab bar. All
those things in the tab bar. It's too bad I don't really
have a tab bar, I wanted to show you this VCL thing.
But those ones get created when you click on the tab for
the first time and they live forever. Okay,
they never go away. And when you click on the tab,
it comes back, it's still exactly the same way.
It's not a segue,
in other words the tab bar is not segueing.
Navigation control and split view are segueing, tab bar,
notice we never did anything there to do a segue, okay? So,
yeah, notice here also that even though when I clicked on
here to show this, look what happened to Emotions 1,
it got laid out a couple times even though its size did not
change. Here I'll do it again. We'll go to happy. Okay,
I didn't change, this did not change size in the least.
Okay, and yet it got viewDidLayoutSubviews,
viewDidLayoutSubview. Okay, so you have to be prepared for
that being called all the time, okay? And so here is
Face 3, it's getting pulled out of the storyboard. It's
kind of interesting that it gets a viewWillDisappear here.
I'm not sure why it gets that right there. Kind of strange
I've noticed this,
and then it loads, it gets a WillAppear it lays out,
it gets DidDisappear, and then DidAppear. So I, this is
strange, I don't really understand why it goes through
that shenanigan right there, but the good news is that
once viewDidAppear happens, it has appeared so
that's good. It's just kind of strange, so be prepared for
that. Now you'll have this code of mine,
this little logging thing. So
you can always throw this in your own app, okay, change
the name to the classes. And then you can see if
somethings not going the way you expect and the lifecycle
method is not getting called at the time you want,
you can see when it's happening exactly. Okay, all
right, that is it for today. Your assignment is posted.
I already explained what it's gonna be.
It's due next Wednesday before class. Hopefully you've
finished up all of the reading for the Swift thing.
All that Swift reading, you're really gonna want to have that
in your memory bank as the rest of the course happens.
So if you're a little behind there,
make sure you catch up as soon as possible. All right, I'll
be here if you have questions. >> For
more, please visit us as stanford.edu.